A Guide to the Papers of W. Fred Duckworth, 1940's-1970's
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Papers of W. Fred Duckworth 1940's-1970's
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 45
This collection consists of 2 Hollinger Boxes and 9 Oversize Boxes.
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Fred Duckworth was born June 20, 1899 in Brevard, North Carolina. He graduated from Kernersville High School in Kernersville, North Carolina, and attended Davidson College in Davidson, North Carolina. He served in the Infantry during World War I. Duckworth married Gertrude Summers, a native of Statesville, North Carolina. Together they had one daughter, Betty.
Mr. Duckworth's first employment was with the Ford Motor Company Assembly Plant in Charlotte, North Carolina in 1920. In 1931, he was promoted to manager of the plant. Then in 1933, he transferred to the Memphis Tennessee Plant. In 1936, Duckworth moved to Norfolk, Virginia to manage the Norfolk Plant. He worked for the Ford Motor Company until 1942.
Mr. Duckworth served his country again from 1942 to 1944, as Regional Director of the War Production Board in Cleveland, Ohio. After this he became an independent businessman, founding the Cavalier Motor Company in Norfolk, Virginia. He served as President of the company until 1959. After that, he continued to serve as Chairman of the Board.
In 1950, running on the coalition ticket, Duckworth was elected as mayor of Norfolk. He served in this position for twelve years, as Norfolk's longest running mayor. He finally declined reelection in 1962. During his terms in office, he was instrumental in converting the "old seaport city" with its slums, crime, run down buildings, and poorly designed streets into the respectable town that received the "All American City" award in 1960. He was considered stubborn and brusque, but he got things done. For better or worse, he often overstepped the political bureaucracy of the city. Among his accomplishments were slum clearance, an industrial park, the Norfolk bridges and tunnels, and the General Douglas MacArthur Memorial in Norfolk's old Court House.
On March 4, 1972, William Fred Duckworth was killed in a barrage of gunfire while taking his regular nightly walk near his Norfolk apartment. Duckworth was shot as many as twelve times from ground level. He was found by a passing motorist, and there were no witnesses. His cane was broken, which indicated to police that there might have been a fight. Robbery was ruled out, as nothing was stolen. No one was ever charged with the crime. Years later the identity of his killer remains a mystery.
Scope and Content Information
The W. Fred Duckworth Papers consists of documents, artifacts, newspaper clippings, photos, and scrapbooks documenting his activities in politics, as a businessman, and as a civic leader. Material dates from the 1940's through the 1970's.
Organization
The collection is broken down into the following series: I: Papers; II: Memorabilia; III: Oversize Photographs and certificates; and IV: Oversize Albums and Scrapbooks.
Series I: Papers. This series is divided into three sub-series. Sub-series A: W. Fred Duckworth; Sub-series B: General Douglas MacArthur; and Sub-series C: Governor Thomas B. Stanley.
Sub-series A: W. Fred Duckworth. This sub-series contains biographical and historical information on William Fred Duckworth. Included are newspaper clippings, correspondence, programs, and unframed certificates. A bulk of the materials relates to Mr. Duckworth's untimely death in 1972. Of particular note is the transcript of the 1962 WTAR presentation "The Duckworth Years" highlighting Mr. Duckworth's career as Mayor of Norfolk. Materials date from the 1950's, 1960's, and 1970's.
Sub-series B: General Douglas MacArthur. This sub-series is devoted to General Douglas MacArthur's death and funeral in 1964.
Sub-series C: Governor Thomas B. Stanley. This sub-series contains information on Virginia Governor Thomas B. Stanley. Included are a program for a dinner in honor of Governor Stanley and information on Virginia's 350th Anniversary Tour of Europe. This tour was a prelude to the observance of the anniversary of the first permanent English settlement in Jamestown. Material dates from September to November 1956.
Series II: Memorabilia. This series contains various memorabilia from Mr. Duckworth's life. Included are items that relate to his career as Norfolk Mayor and items that reflect his various civic involvements.
Series III: Oversize Photographs and Certificates. This sub-series contains photographs and certificates of importance to Fred Duckworth. Most of these are framed. Many of the photographs are of Mr. Duckworth. There are also photos of General Douglas MacArthur, as well as other military, political, and civic leaders. There are a few photos related to Mr. Duckworth's career with Ford. Certificates from various organizations and councils recognize work and accomplishments. A 1957 framed certificate from President Dwight Eisenhower appoints Mr. Duckworth a member of the Water Pollution Control Advisory Board in the Public Health Service.
Series IV: Oversize Albums, and Scrapbooks. This sub-series contains albums, scrapbooks, and books related to Mr. Duckworth's activities. Many contain material from his time working for Ford. Other material relates to his terms as Mayor of Norfolk.
Container List
- Papers
  - W. Fred Duckworth
    - Biographical Information (Box 1:1)
    - Certificate of Honorary Membership in People-to-People (Box 1:2)
    - Honorary Alumni - Chesapeake College (Box 1:3)
    - Honorary Diploma - Douglas MacArthur Academy, June 3, 1965 (Box 1:4)
    - Honorary Doctor of Laws Degree Speech, Howard Payne College, October 18, 1969 (Box 1:5)
    - WTAR Presentation on "The Duckworth Years", August 23, 1962 (Box 1:6)
    - Account of 1959 European Tour, Iula Convention, Berlin, Germany (Box 1:7)
    - Prayer and Hymn for W. Fred Duckworth Funeral Service, First Presbyterian Church, Ohoskie, North Carolina (Box 1:8)
    - Sympathy Cards and Letters regarding Fred Duckworth's death, March 1972 (Box 1:9)
    - Duckworth Memorial Contributions - Letters (Box 1:10)
    - Memorial Resolutions - MacArthur Memorial Foundation, Board of Directors, March 16, 1972 (Box 1:11)
    - Memorial Resolution - Tidewater Virginia Development Council, April 13, 1972 (Box 1:12)
    - Memorial Resolution - Virginia Bankers Association, June 1972 (Box 1:13)
    - Memorial Resolution - Virginia National Bank, July 14, 1972 (Box 1:14)
    - Duckworth Plaque - Unveiling, April 12, 1973 (Box 1:15)
    - Duckworth Plaque - Inscription, April 13, 1973 (Box 1:16)
    - Clippings - Political 1960's I (Box 1:17)
    - Clippings - Political 1960's II (Box 1:18)
    - Clippings - W. Fred Duckworth (Box 1:19)
    - Clippings - "MacArthur Memorial's W. Fred Duckworth Slain", Nashville Banner, March 4, 1972 (Box 1:20)
    - Clippings - Duckworth Slaying, March 1972 (Box 1:21)
    - Clippings - "Duckworth Slaying Still a Mystery", Virginian Pilot, January 2, 1979 (Box 1:22)
    - U.S.S. Norfolk Commissions March 4, 1953 (Box-folder 2:1)
    - Photo, Fred Duckworth & W.E. Norman, Opening March 7, 1951 (Box-folder 2:2)
    - Legal Documents and Memorandum of Association, Standard Marine Insurance Company Limited (Box-folder 2:3)
    - Black & White Photos -- Duckworth Demolition Ceremony 1951 (Box-folder 2:4)
    - Color Photo / Portrait of Duckworth & Joseph Healy (1960's-1970's?) (Box-folder 2:5)
    - Black & White Photos / Portraits of Fred Duckworth undated (Box-folder 2:6)
    - Black & White Photos of the First Visit of the U.S.S. Norfolk to Norfolk, VA March 1954 (Box-folder 2:7)
    - Ancient & Accepted Scottish Rite, Southern Jurisdiction, USA, Supreme Council, 33* October 1971 Session (Box-folder 2:8)
  - General Douglas MacArthur
    - General Douglas MacArthur: Last Journey for an Old Soldier (Box 2:9)
    - Clippings - Douglas MacArthur Death, April 5, 1964 I (Box 2:10)
    - Clippings - Douglas MacArthur Death, April 5, 1964 II (Box 2:11)
    - Clippings - Douglas MacArthur Death, April 5, 1964 III (Box 2:12)
    - General Douglas MacArthur Funeral Service, April 11, 1964 (Box 2:13)
    - General Douglas MacArthur Memorial (Box 2:14)
  - Governor Thomas B. Stanley
    - Inscribed Program in Honor of Governor Thomas B. Stanley, October 27, 1956 (Box 2:15)
    - Booklet on the Virginia 350th Anniversary Tour of Europe, Sept. 29 - Nov. 5, 1956 (Box 2:16)
    - Itineraries of the Virginia Commemorative Visit to Europe, Sept. 29 - Nov. 5, 1956 (Box 2:17)
    - Lists of Members of the Party, Virginia Commemorative Visit to Europe, Sept. 29 - Nov. 5, 1956 (Box 2:18)
- Memorabilia
  - Three Webster School Notebooks (Box 2:19)
  - The Elementary Spelling Book, 1908 (Box 2:20)
  - Academic Hood (Box 3:1)
  - Shriner's hat and case (possibly Mason's hat) (Box 3:2)
  - Three Wooden Gavels (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Plaque from U.S. Naval Academy Midshipmen, Class of 1961 (Box 3:4)
  - City of Norfolk, Sept. 1950 - Aug. 1962, Memorial, Wood (Box 3:5)
  - "Mr. Duckworth, President of the Council" Wooden Name Plate (Box-folder 3:6)
  - "W.F.Duckworth," Wooden Name Plate with Metal (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Brass Ship with Chain (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Wooden Gavel Base (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Yellow Pine, Key to the City of Bogalusa, Louisiana (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Shriner's Oasis Fez Hat with case (Box 3:11)
  - Rotary International Pin (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel Tile (Box 4:1)
  - Mace Clasp (Box 4:2)
  - Dare County and Cape Hatteras Lighthouse Centennial Medallion (Box 4:3)
  - Key from Bethlehem (Box 4:4)
  - Pen knife and box (Box 4:5)
  - Square containing barbed wire from the Iron Curtain, presented by the Radio Free Europe Fund (Box 4:6)
  - Mason Medallion, Frederick the Great (two copies) (Box 4:7)
  - R.O.J. pendant (Box 4:8)
  - SEMCO clock and case (Box 4:9)
  - Asssorted campaign buttons (Goldwater & Byrd pins [2], Goldwater 1964 pins [2], Broyhill for Congress, IKE gold pin, gold elephant with glasses pin, Robertson for Senate pin, Byrd for Senator pin, white and red elephant clossione pin) (Box 4:10)
  - Eastern Gas and Fuel Associates file clip (Box 4:11)
  - Virginia Dare Medallion (Box 4:12)
  - Wilmington N.C. Key-"Azalea Capital of the World" c. 1959 (Box 4:13)
  - Pedometer (Box 4:14)
  - Cosmopolitan Club Distinguished Service Medal (Box 4:15)
  - Deputy Sheriff's Badge, Mecklenburg County, N.C. (Box 4:16)
  - Hammer with Spherical Head (Box-folder 4:17)
  - National Seal (Box-folder 4:18)
- Oversize Photographs and Certificates
  - Color print of jungle warfare and signature of Douglas Mac Arthur. (Box 5:1)
  - Manila-folder containing inscribed black and white photograph of Douglas Mac Arthur landing in the Philippines in 1944. (Box 5:2)
  - Envelope containing 24 color photographs, of dedication of Mac Arthur Memorial. (Box 5:3)
  - "Photographs" album of photographs and news clippings, 1946 District Dealer Meetings, Southeastern Region (Box 5:4)
  - "National Ford Dealers Council," Dearborn, Michigan, October 7,8, and 9, 1946, album of W.F Duckworth: photographs (Box 5:5)
  - Red photograph album containing black and white photographs taken during trip to Europe in 1961. (Box 5:6)
  - Blue photograph album with note from Bob Havins of Howard Payne college, October 18th, 1969. (Box 5:7)
  - Doctor of Laws certificate presented to W. Fred Duckworth by Howard Payne College,October 18th, 1969 (Box 5:8)
  - Scrapbook containing photographs of W.F. Duckworth visiting the Schultheiss Brewery, Berlin-Spandau, on June 22, 1959, with letter of invitation, June 17 1959, also enclosed is an invitation to a reception on June 20, 1959, from the American Municipal Association. (Box 5:9)
  - Framed certificate-granting status of "Honorary Alumnus of the Armed Forces Staff College" to Hon. W. Fred Duckworth (#31) (Box 6:1)
  - Framed black and white photograph of Mayor Duckworth and others at International Fleet Review, with inscription, June 12, 1957 (#12) (Box 6:2)
  - Framed citation presented to Hon. W. Fred Duckworth by the military order of the world wars in recognition of his part in establishing the Mac Arthur Memorial, October 9th, 1964 (#27) (Box 6:3)
  - Framed color photograph of the U.S.S Norfolk with inscription by the captain (#9) (Box 6:4)
  - Framed black and white photograph of the launching of the USS Norfolk (Box 7:1)
  - Framed, Black & White Photograph of Fred Duckworth at the Launching of the U.S.S. Norfolk (#6) (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Framed black and white photograph of Councilman Lawrence Page, with inscription (#10) (Box 7:3)
  - Framed color photograph of Queen Elizabeth II, with blue ribbon enclosed (#2) (Box 7:4)
  - Framed color photograph of Admiral Thomas Moorer with inscription to Fred Duckworth (#3) (Box 7:5)
  - Framed resolution of Norfolk Rotary Club in memory of W. Fred Duckworth, March 7, 1972 (#3) (Box 7:6)
  - Framed citation presented to Hon. William Frederick Duckworth with the 1956 Distinguished Service Medal awarded by the Cosmopolitan Club of Norfolk (#26-A) (Box 7:7)
  - Framed color photograph of Admiral Page Smith, with inscription (Box 7:8)
  - Framed color photograph of Admiral Robert Dennison, with inscription (Box 7:9)
  - Photographs of Fred Duckworth and color photograph of Mrs. Duckworth (#15) (Box 8:1)
  - Folder from James T. White & Company containing black and white photographs of Fred Duckworth for the National Cyclopedia of American Biography(#17) (Box 8:2)
  - Black and white photograph of naval officer and six women re: Scholarship Award with accompanying note from John Funk (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Black and white photograph of 130 Ford Salesmen who won the trip to World's Fair in Chicago. (Box 8:4)
  - Photograph holder with photograph of Norfolk City Council, 1950: E.V. Griffin, George L. Abbott, F. Duckworth, Lawrence Page, and N.B. Etheridge (Box 8:5)
  - Framed Certificate of Appreciation to William Frederick Duckworth from eight civic organizations, September 6, 1972 (Box 9:1)
  - Framed certificate from President Eisenhower to William F. Duckworth, appointing him a member of the Water Pollution Control Advisory Board in the Public Health Service, September 26, 1957 (this item is unboxed) (Box 9:2)
  - Framed Resolution Honoring W. Fred Duckworth on his Death by the State Highway Commission March 16, 1972 (Box-folder 9:3)
  - House Joint Resolution No. 162 of the Virginia General Assembly honoring Fred Duckworth after his death, March 7, 1972 (Box 10:1)
  - Posthumous Special Service Award from the Virginia State Chamber of Commerce, May 10, 1972 (Box 10:2)
  - Mason certificate as Knight Commander (Box 10:3)
  - Mason certificate as Master of the Royal Secret (Box 10:4)
  - Mason certificate as Honorary Inspector General (Box 10:5)
- Oversize Albums and Scrapbooks
  - "Ford-O-Graphs" Album of W. F. Duckworth, 1951 Activities: Photographs and News Clippings (Box 11:1)
  - "Ford Close-ups" Album of W.F. Duckworth: Photographs of Henry Ford (Box 11:2)
  - "Strictly Personal" Album of W.F. Duckworth, 1950 Activities: Flier, Program, and News Clippings. (Box 11:3)
  - Book: A New Era Opens: Chesapeake Bay Bridge-Tunnel, April 15, 1964, with News Clippings, Programs, and Inserts. (Box 11:4)
  - White Album Containing Resolutions Passed in Honor of W. Fred Duckworth Following his Death in 1972. (Box 12:1)
  - White scrapbook of W. Fred Duckworth, March 3, 1972: News Clippings (Box 12:2)
  - Brown Scrapbook Containing Entries from 1956 and 1957 (Box 12:3)
  - Binder of Materials from the Douglas MacArthur Academy of Freedom of Howard Payne College, Including Papers and 13 Black and White Photographs. (Box 13:1)
  - College of William and Mary Scrapbook to W. Fred Duckworth 1964 (Box-folder 14:1)
  - W. Fred Duckworth: Ford Motor Company Scrapbook 1924-1963 (Box-folder 14:2)
  - Wooden Scrapbook 1958-1963 (Box-folder 15:1)
  - Green Scrapbook 1951-1957 (Box-folder 16:1)
  - Framed City Council resolution in honor of Mayor Duckworth in leaving the City Council, August 1962 (#24) (Box 17:1)
  - Framed certificate from President Eisenhower to William F. Duckworth, appointing him a member of the Water Pollution Control Advisory Board in the Public Health Service, September 26, 1957 (this item is unboxed) (Box 18:1)